本节我们看如何使用分组密码加密多个明文信息
In this segment we will look at how to use
block ciphers to encrypt multiple messages
使用同样的密钥。这个在实际中有用
比如在文件系统中
using the same key. This comes up in
practice for example in file systems where
使用相同的密钥加密多个文件
在网络协议中
the same key's used to encrypt multiple
files. It comes up in networking protocols
使用同样的密钥加密多个数据包
where the same key is used to encrypt
multiple packets. So let's see how to do
我们看怎么办。首先我们需要定义
it. The first thing we need to do is to
define what is mean for a cipher to be
密码是安全的意义，当同样的密钥被用于
加密多个信息时
secure when the same key is used to
encrypt multiple messages. When we use the
当我们多次使用密钥，那么结果是
攻击者获得很多用同一个密钥加密的密文
key more than once the result of that is
that the adversary gets to see many cyber
因此，当我们定义安全的时候
text encrypted using the same key. As a
result, when we define security, we're
我们允许攻击者实施选择明文攻击
gonna allow the adversary to mount what's
called a chosen plain text attack. In
换句话说，攻击者可以获得他选择的任一明文的加密
other words, the adversary can obtain the
encryption of arbitrary messages of his
例如，如果攻击者正和Alice交互
choice. So, for example, if the
adversary's interacting with Alice. The
攻击者可以让Alice加密任何他选择的明文
adversary can ask Alice to encrypt
arbitrary messages of the adversary's
Alice会加密那些信息
choosing. And Alice will go ahead and
encrypt those messages and give the
然后给攻击者相应的密文。大家可能会怀疑
Alice会做这些
adversary the resulting cipher texts. You
might wonder why would Alice ever do this.
这点在现实中是怎么发生的呢？
How could this possibly happen in real
life? But it turns out this is actually
但事实上这点在实际中很常见。事实上
在现实里，这个模型还算保守的
very common in real life. And in fact,
this modeling is quite a conservative
比如说，攻击者可能发给Alice一份电子邮件
modeling of real life. For example, the
adversary might send Alice an email. When
当Alice收到这份电子邮件时，邮件被写进加密的硬盘里
Alice receives the email, the writes it to
her encrypted disk, thereby encrypting the
使用她的密钥加密攻击者的电子邮件
如果后来攻击者偷到了这个硬盘
adversary's email using her secret key. If
later the adversary steals this disc, then
那么他就可以获得这份发给Alice的
电子邮件的加密，使用Alice的密钥
he obtains the encryption of an email that
he sent Alice under Alice's secret key. So
这就是一个选择明文攻击的例子
攻击者提供给Alice明文
that's an example of a chosen plain text
attack, where the adversary provided Alice
Alice用自己的密钥加密这个明文
with a message and she encrypted that
message using her own key. And then later
之后攻击者能够获得相应的密文
the attacker was able to obtain the
resulting cipher text. So that's the
这是攻击者的能力。他的目标是
adversary's power. And then the
adversary's goal is basically to break
破解语义安全。那么我们要更清楚地定义这点
semantic security. So let's define this
more precisely. As usual, we're gonna
通常，我们在选择明文攻击下定义语义安全
要使用两个实验
define semantic security under a chosen
plain text attack using two experiments,
实验0和实验1，是关于挑战者和攻击者之间的
一个游戏模型
experiment zero and experiment one, that
are modeled as a game between a challenger
当游戏开始时，挑战者选择一个随机密钥K
and an adversary. When the game begins,
the challenger is gonna choose a random
现在攻击者询问挑战者
key K. And now the adversary basically
gets to query the challenger. So the
攻击者提交一个语义安全询问
adversary now begins by submitting a
semantic security query, namely, he
他提交两个明文M0和M1
我多加了个下标，但我先忽略它们一会
submits two messages, M zero and M one. I
added another index, but let me ignore
那么攻击者提交了两个明文M0和M1
that extra index for a while. So the
adversary submits two messages, M zero and
它们的长度是一样的。然后攻击者收到
M one, that happen to be of the same
length. And then the adversary receives
提交的明文的加密，M0或M1的
the encryption of one of those messages,
either of M zero or of M one. In
在实验0中，他收到M0的加密结果
experiment zero, he receives the
encryption of M zero. In experiment one,
在实验1中，他收到M1的加密结果
目前这和一个标准的语义安全游戏
he receives the encryption of M one. So,
so far this would look familiar this looks
一模一样。但是对选择明文攻击
exactly like a standard semantic security
game. However, plain text attack
攻击者可以重复这个询问
the adversary can now repeat this query
again. So now you can issue a query with
现在你发起了其他两个明文的询问，长度相同
two other plain texts, again of the same
length, and again you would receive the
你还会收到其中之一的加密。在实验0中
你会收到M0的加密
encryption of one of them. In experiment
zero you would receive the encryption of M
在实验1中，你会收到M1的加密
zero. In experiment one you would receive
the encryption of M one. And the attacker
攻击者还可以继续这样的询问
事实上，我们说他可以进行最多Q次
can continue issuing queries like this. In
fact we'll say that he can issue up to Q
这样的询问。然后记住，每次他都询问一对明文
queries of this type. And then, remember,
every time he issues a pair of messages.
这对明文长度相同，他会获得
That happen to be of the same length and
every time he either gets the encryption
左边或右边的加密结果
在实验0里，他总是获得
of the left side or the right side. Again
in experiment zero he will always get the
左边明文的加密。在实验1里，
他总是获得右边明文的加密
encryption of the left message; in
experiment one he will always get the
攻击者的目标是算出
encryption of the right message. And, then
adversary's goal is, basically, to figure
他是在实验0中，还是实验1中
out whether he's in experimental zero or
in experiment one. In other words, whether
换句话说，他一直在接收左边信息的加密
还是右边信息的加密
he was constantly receiving the encryption
of the left message or the encryption of
那么，某种意义上，这是一个标准的
语义安全游戏
the right message. So, in some sense, this
is a standard semantic security game just
只不过重复多次询问，每次询问后
攻击者可以进行调整
iterated over many queries that the
attacker can issue to adaptively one after
现在选择明文攻击的本质就在于
the other. Now the chosen plain text
attack is captured by the fact that if the
如果攻击者想知道特定明文信息m的加密
attacker wants the encryption of a
particular message m. What he could do is,
比如使用询问J，查明文J的加密结果
在询问J中，他把信息0和信息1
for example, use query J for some J, where
in this query J he'll set both the zero
都设为一样的信息M。换句话说
message and the one message to be the
exactly same message M. In other words,
左边和右边的信息是一样的
both the left message and the right
message are the same, and both are set to
两遍信息都是M。这时由于两个信息一样
the message M. In this case, what he will
receive, since both messages are the same,
攻击者会收到他感兴趣的信息M的加密结果
he knows that he's gonna receive the
encryption of this message M that he was
这正是选择明文攻击的意思
interested in. So this is exactly what we
meant by a chosen plaintext attack.
攻击者可以提交信息m，收到m的加密
Where the adversary can submit a message m
and receive the encryption of that
m是他自己选的。那么他的一些询问
particular message m of his choice. So
some of his queries might be of this chose
可以是选择明文攻击的方式
即左右信息是一样的
plain text flavor where the message on the
left is equal to the message on the right,
但另一些询问可以是标准的语义安全的
but some of the queries might be standard
semantic security queries where the two
即两个信息是不同的，这可以给攻击者
一些信息，关于是实验0还是实验1的
messages are distinct and that actually
gives him information on whether he's in
现在大家应该对这类定义习惯了
experiment zero or in experiment one. Now
by now you should be used to this
当我们说系统是在选择明文攻击下语义安全的
definition where we say that the system is
semantically secure under a chosen plain
如果所有有效的攻击者
text attack. If, for all efficient
adversaries, they cannot distinguish
都无法区分实验0和实验1，换句话说
experiment zero from experiment one. In
other words, the probability that, at the
输出b'的概率，即实验b的输出概率
end, the output, B Prime, which we're
gonna denote by the output of experiment
这个输出无论在实验0还是实验1里都是一样的
B. This output will be the same whether
in experiment zero or experiment
那么攻击者无法区分他总是收到
one. So the attacker couldn't distinguish
between always receiving encryptions of
左边信息的加密，或是右边信息的加密
the left messages, versus always receiving
encryptions of the right messages. So in
大家考虑一个可以实施选择明文攻击的攻击者
your mind, I'd like you to be thinking of
an adversary that is able to mount a
可以获得他选择的任意信息的加密
chosen plaintext attack, namely, be given
the encryption of arbitrary messages of
他的目标是为其他密文破解语义安全
his choice, and his goal is to break
semantic security for some other challenge
我说过在这个真实的游戏模型里
cipher texts. And as I said in this
game model of the real world the
攻击者可以欺骗Alice，为他所选择的明文加密
attacker is able to fool Alice into
encrypting for him messages of his choice
然后攻击者的目标是破解某些挑战的密文
and then the attacker's goal is to somehow
break some challenge cypher text. So I
那么我说目前我们看到过的所有密码
claim that all the ciphers that we've seen
up until now, namely deterministic counter
确定的计数器模式或是一次性密码本
在选择明文攻击下是不安全的
mode or the one time pad, are insecure
under a chosen plain text attack. More
一般地，假设我们有一个加密机制
generally, suppose we have an encryption
scheme that always outputs the same cipher
总是对信息M输出同样的密文。换句话说
如果我让这个加密机制加密信息M
text for a particular message M. In other
words, if I ask the encryption scheme to
那么我让这个加密机制再次加密信息M
encrypt the message M once. And then I ask
the encryption scheme to encrypt the
两次加密机制都输出一样的密文
message M again. If in both cases the
encryption scheme outputs the same cypher
这样系统在选择明文攻击下不可能是安全的
text, then that system cannot possibly be
secure under a chosen plain text attack.
确定的计数器模式和一次性密码本都是如此
And both deterministic counter mode and
the one time pad were of that flavor. They
它们总是对相同的输入信息，输出相同的密文
always output the same cipher text, given
the same message. And so let's see why
我没看为什么它们对选择明文攻击不安全
这种攻击是简单的
that cannot be chosen plain text secure.
And the attack is fairly simple, what the
攻击者两次输出同样的明文
attacker is gonna do, is he's gonna output
the same message twice. This just says.
他非常想知道M0的加密
这里攻击者得到了C0
That he really wants the encryption of M0.
So here the attacker is given C0 which is
也就是M0的密文。那么这是他的选择明文攻击
the encryption of M0. So this was his
chosen plain text query where he actually
他收到了他选择的M0的加密
received the encryption of the message M0
of his choice. And now he's going to break
现在他要破解语义安全。他输出两个明文M0和M1
semantic security. So what he does is he
outputs two messages, M0 and M1 of the
两个明文长度相同。攻击者还有明文Mb的加密
same length, and he's going to be given
the encryption of MB. But low and behold,
我们说这个加密系统在加密M0时
we said that the encryption system always
outputs the same cipher text when its
总是输出同样的密文。因此，如果b等于0
encrypting the message, M0. Therefore, if
B is equal to zero, we know that C, this
那么挑战者的密文C就等于C0
因为它是M0的加密结果
challenged cipher text, is simply euqal to CO,
because it's the encryption of M0.
但是如果b=1，那么挑战者的密文
However, if B is=to one. Then we know that
this challenge cypher text is the
就是M1的加密结果，即不是C0
encryption of M1 which is something other
than C zero. So all the attacker does is he
所以攻击者只需检查C是否等于C0
或者说，他是否输出1
just checks his C is = to C0 the output's
zero in other words he outputs one. So, in
这时，攻击者完全能够猜出位b
this case, the attacker is able to
perfectly guess this bit B, so he knows
攻击者能确切地知道结果，给定M0的加密
或者给定M1的加密
exactly what was given the encryption
of M0, or the encryption of M1. And as a
因此，攻击者获胜的优势是1，意味着
result, his advantage in winning this game
is one. Meaning that the system cannot
这个系统对CPA不可能是安全的
1不是一个可忽略的数
possibly be CPA secure. One is not a
negligible number. So this shows that the
那么这就证明了确定的加密机制不可能是CPA安全的
deterministic encryption schemes cannot
possibly be CPA-secure, but you might
但是大家可能会怀疑，这在现实中有何意义呢？
wonder well, what does this mean in
practice? Well in practice this means
在现实中这意味着每一个信息总是被
加密成相同的密文
again that every message is always
encrypted to the same cipher text. What
这意味着如果你加密硬盘上的文件
this means is if you're encrypting files
on disk, and you happen to be encrypting
如果加密的两个文件正好一样，则它们的密文
two files that happen to be the same, they
will result in the same cipher text and
是一样的，然后攻击者看硬盘的时候
then the attacker by looking at the
encrypted disk, will learn that these two
就会知道这两个文件实际上包含了相同的信息
尽管攻击者可能不知道具体内容
files actually contain the same content.
The attacker might not learn what the
但他会学到一点，这两文件是同一内容的加密
content is, but he will learn that these
two encrypted files are an encryption of
而这一点他本不应该知道的。类似地
the same content and he shouldn't be able
to learn that. Similarly, if you send two
如果你发送两个加密的网络数据包
它们正好是一样的
encrypted packets on the network that
happen to be the same, the attacker will
攻击者不会知道数据包内容是什么
但他会知道这两个包是同样的内容
not learn the content of those packets,
but he will learn that those two packets
想一个关于加密语音通话的例子
actually contain the same information.
Think for example of an encrypted voice
每次当线上没有声音的时候
conversation. Every time there's quiet on
the line, the system will be sending
系统会发送全是0的加密。但是由于0的加密
encryptions of zero. But since encryption
of zero are always mapped to the same
总是被映射成相同的密文，攻击者监听网络
cypher text. An attacker looking at the
network will be able to identify exactly
就可以分辨出通话中哪些时候是安静的
the points in the conversation where
there's quiet because he will always see
因为他每次总是看到一样的密文
那么这些例子说明
those exact same cypher text every time.
So these are examples where deterministic
确定的加密不可能是安全的。形式化地说
encryption cannot possibly be secure. And
as I say formerly we say that the
确定的加密对于选择明文攻击
不可能是语义安全的
deterministic encryption can not be
semantically secure under a chosen plain
这里的教训是，如果要用密钥
text attack. So what do we do, well the
lesson here is if the secret keys gonna be
加密多个明文信息，最好是
used to encrypt multiple messages, it had
better be the case that given the same
给两次同样的明文去加密，
加密算法可以产生不同的密文
plain text to encrypt twice. The
encryption algorithm must produce
有两种方法可以做到
different cipher texts. And so there are
two ways to do that. The first method is
第一种叫做随机加密，这种加密算法
what's called randomized encryption. Here,
the encryption algorithm itself is going
在加密过程中选择一些随机的字符串
to choose some random string during the
encryption process and it is going to
他将使用这个随机字符串来加密信息M
encrypt the message M using that random
string. So what this means is that a
这意味着特定的信息，比如M0
不会被映射到一个密文
particular message, M0 for example, isn't
just going to be mapped to one cipher text
而是被映射到一组密文
but it's going to be mapped to a whole
ball of cipher texts. Whereon every
每次加密，我们输出这个球里的一个点
那么我们每次加密时
encryption, basically, we output one point
in this ball. So every time we encrypt, the
加密算法选择一个随机字符串
encryption algorithm chooses a random
string, and that random string leads to
这个随机字符串射到球里的一点
当然，解密算法总是将球里的任一点
one point in this ball. Of course, the
decryption algorithm, when it takes any
映射到M0。类似地，明文M1
point in this ball, will always map the
result to M zero. Similarly cipher text M
(口误：cipher->plain)
会被映射到一个球，每次我们加密M1
one will be mapped to a ball, and every
time we encrypt M one, we basically output
我们输出球里的一个点。这些球是不相交的
one point in this ball. And these balls
have to be disjoint, so that the
解密算法获得球里的一点，对应于M1
encryption algorithm, when it obtains a
point in the ball corresponding to M one,
(解密说成加密了)
总是输出明文信息M1。这样，由于加密算法
will always output the message M one. In
this way, since the encryption algorithm
使用了随机性，如果我们加密同样的明文两次
以很高的概率
uses randomness, if we encrypt the same
message twice, with high probability we'll
我会得到不同的密文。很不幸，这意味着
get different cipher texts. Unfortunately
this means that the cipher text
密文一定比明文长，因为
necessarily has to be longer than the
plain text because somehow the randomness
生成密文时使用的随机性，现在被
编码进密文里了
that was used to generate the cipher text
is now encoded somehow in the cipher text.
所以密文需要更多的空间
不严格地讲，密文大小
So the cipher text takes more space. And
roughly speaking, the cipher text size is
要比明文大得多，多出了用于解密的
going to be larger than the plain text. By
basically the number of random bits that
随机位。所有如果明文很长
were used during encryption. So if the
plain texts are very big, if the plain
如果明文有几个G，那么随机位可能有
texts are gigabytes long, the number of
random bits is going to be on the order of
128个。也许这个多余空间无关紧要
128. So maybe this extra space doesn't
really matter. But if the plain texts are
但如果明文很短，也许它们本身就是128位
为每个密文添加128位
very short, maybe they themselves are 128
bits, then adding an extra 128 bits to
就会使整个密文大小翻倍
every cipher text is going to double the
total cipher text size. And that could be
那样开销就太大了。所以我说随机加密很好
quite expensive. So as I say randomized
encryption is a fine solution but in some
但是在某些场合它引入了很大的开销
所以我们看另一个简单的例子
cases it actually introduces quite a bit
of costs. So let's look at a simple example.
那么想象一下，我们有一个伪随机函数
So imagine we have a pseudorandom
function that takes inputs in a certain
其输入来自一个特定空间r，也叫做
新鲜值空间。而输出则来自明文空间
space r which is gonna be called a nonce
space. And outputs, outputs in the message
现在，我们定义下面的随机加密机制
space. And, now, let's define the
following randomize encryption scheme
我们想加密明文m，使用某种加密机制
where we want to encrypt the message m
with the encryption of whatever it's gonna
首先生成一个新鲜值空间R中一个随机值r
do is first it's gonna generate a random r
in this nonce space R. And then it's going
打开一个由两部分组成的密文
第一部分是r值
to open a cypher text that consist of two
components, the first component is going
第二部分是伪随机函数在r的值
to be this value R and the second
component is going to be an evaluation of
与明文M的异或值
the pseudo-random function at the point R
XOR with the message M. And my question to
我的问题是，这个加密系统在选择明文攻击下
是安全的吗？
you is, is this encryption system
semantically secure under a chosen plain
那么正确答案是肯定的。仅当新鲜值空间R
text attack? So the correct answer is yes.
But only if the nonce space R is large
足够大时，r才会以很高的概率不重复
enough so that little R never repeats with
very, very high probability. And let's
我们来看为什么是这样。首先
因为函数F是一个安全的伪随机函数
quickly argue why that's true. So first of
all, because F is a secure pseudo-random
我们还可以用一个真随机函数替换之
function, we might as well replace it with
a truly random function. In other words,
换句话说，这和我们使用真随机函数f
加密明文M是不可区分的
this is indistinguishable from the case
where we encrypt the message M, using the
计算在点r的值，然后与M异或
truly random function little F, evaluated
to point R, and then XOR with M.
但由于这个r不会重复。每个密文
使用不同的r
But since this little r never repeats. Every
cypher text uses a different little r. What
这意味着值F(r)每次都是随机均匀分布的
this means is that the values of F(r)
are random uniform independent strings
相互独立的字符串。所有每次我们加密
一个明文，我们使用的都是一个新的
every time. So every time we encrypt a
message, we encrypt it essentially using a
均匀分布的随机的一次性密码本
由于异或一个均匀分布的字符串
new uniform random one time pad. And since
XORing a uniform string with any string
可以让任何字符串都变成新的均匀分布的字符串
生成的密文就是两个
simply generates a new uniform string, the
resulting cipher text is distributed as
随机字符串的分布。我分别称它们为r和r'
simply two random uniform strings. I'll
call them r and r prime. And so both in
在实验0和实验1中，所有攻击者可以看到
experiment zero and in experiment one, all
the attacker gets to see are truly uniform
真随机字符串r和r'；由于在两个实验中
random strings r, r', and since in both
experiments the attacker is seeing the same
攻击者看到的字符串同分布，他无法区分它们
distribution, he cannot distinguish the
two distributions. And so since security
由于当我们使用真随机函数时，
安全性完全成立，
holds completely when we're using a truly
random function. It's also gonna hold when
当我们使用伪随机函数时，也是有安全性的
好，这是一个很好的例子
we're using a pseudorandom function. Okay,
so this is a nice example of how we use
使用伪随机函数与真随机函数表现很像
the fact that the pseudo random function
behaves like a random function to argue
这一事实来证明这个加密机制的安全性
security of this particular encryption
scheme. Okay, so now we have a nice
现在我们有了一个随机算法的好例子
另一个构造对选择明文攻击安全的加密机制
example of randomized encryption. The
other approach to building chosen plain
的方法是叫做基于新鲜值的加密
text secure encryption schemes is what's
called a nonce based encryption. Now, in
现在，基于新鲜值的加密系统里
加密算法取三个输入
a nonce based encryption system, the
encryption algorithm actually takes three
而不是两个输入。通常它取密钥和明文信息
inputs rather than two. As usual it takes
the key and the message. But it also takes
但它还另外一个输入叫做新鲜值
类似地，解密算法
an additional input called a nonce. And
similarly, the decryption algorithm also
也取新鲜值为输入，然后输出明文的加密
takes the nonce as input, and then produces
the resulting decrypted plain text. And
这个新鲜值n是什么？这个新鲜值是公开的
what is this nonce value n? This nonce is
a public value. It does not need to be
它没有必要向攻击者隐瞒
但唯一的要求是
hidden from the adversary but the only
requirement is that the pair (k,n)
(k,n)只能用来加密一个明文
换句话说，这一对(k,n)
is only used to encrypt a single
message. In other words, this pair (k,n)
加密不同明文时必须更换
有两种方法可以改变
must change from message to message. And
there are two ways to change it. One way
一种是为每个明文选择新的随机密钥
to change it is by choosing a new random
key for every message. And the other way
另一种是保持密钥不变，然后选择新的新鲜值
is to keep using the same key all the time
but then we must choose a new nonce for
我说过，我想强调这点，新鲜值
every message. And, and as I said, I wanna
emphasize again, this nonce need not
不是私密的，它也不需要是随机的
唯一的要求是新鲜值是唯一的
be secret, and it need not be random. The
only requirement is the nonce is unique.
事实上，我们要用新鲜值这个术语
贯穿整个课程
And in fact, we're gonna use this
term throughout the course. A nonce
一个新鲜值意味着不能重复
它不必是随机的
for us, means a unique value that doesn't
repeat. It does not have to be random. So
那么我们看选择新鲜值的几个例子
最简单的选择是
let's look at some examples of choosing an
nonce, well the simplest option is
就把计数器当成是新鲜值
simply to make the nonce be a
counter. So for example the networking
例如在网络协议中，你可以把新鲜值想象成
数据包的计数器
protocol you can imagine the nonce
being a packet counter that's incremented
发送方每发出一个包，或接收方每接到一个包
计数器加一
every time a packet is sent by a sender or
received by the receiver. This means that
这意味着加密者必须在信息间保留状态记录
the encrypter has to keep state from
message to message mainly that he has to
他必须保留这个计数器，每条信息传送时
计数器加一
keep this counter around and increment it
after every message is transmitted.
有趣的是，如果解密者具有同样的状态
Interestingly, if the decrypter actually
has the same state then there is no need
是不需要在密文里包括新鲜值的
因为新鲜值是隐藏的
to include the nonce in the cipher text
since the nonce is implicit. Let's look
我们看一个例子。HTTPS协议运行在一个可靠的传输机制上
at an example. The https protocol is run
over a reliable transport mechanism which
意思是发送方发送的数据包，
接收方是按发送顺序接收的
means that packets sent by the sender are
assumed to be received in order at a
所以如果发送者发送了数据包5，然后
发送了数据包6
recipient. So if the sender sends packet #5
and then packet #6, the recipient
接收方会接收到数据包5，然后是
数据包6，以这个顺序
will receive packet #5 and then
packet #6 in that order. This
这意味着如果发送方维护了一个数据包计数器
means that if the sender maintains a
packet counter, the recipient can also
接收方也可以维护一个计数器
两个计数器是同步增长的
maintain a packet counter and two counters
basically increment in sync. In this case
这种情况下就不需要把新鲜值包含在数据包里
there is no reason to include the
nonce in the packets because the
因为新鲜值对于双方来说都是隐藏的
但是，在其他协议中
nonce is implicit between the two
sides. However, in other protocols, for
例如IPsec，一个用来加密IP层的协议
example, in IPsec, IPsec is a protocol
designed to encrypt the IP layer. The IP
IP层是不能保证数据包按序送达的
所以发送方发送包5
layer does not guarantee in order
delivery. And so the sender might send
再发送包6，但有可能以相反的顺序
packet #5 and then packet #6, but
those will be received in reverse order at
被接收方接收。这种情况下也是可以用
数据包计数器作为新鲜值的
the recipient. In this case it's still
fine to use a packet counter as a nonce
现在新鲜值必须被包含在数据包里了
but now the nonce has to be included in
the packet so that the recipient knows
这样接收方才知道该使用那一个新鲜值
来解密收到的数据包。如我所说
which nonce to use to decrypt the
received packet. So as I say, nonce based
基于新鲜值的加密是一个非常有效的方法
来实现对CPA的安全。特别地
encryption is a very efficient way to
achieve CPA security. In particular if the
如果新鲜值是隐藏，它甚至不会增加密文长度
nonce is implicit, it doesn't even
increase the cipher text length. Of course
当然另一个生成唯一新鲜值的方法是
随机选取新鲜值
another method to generate a unique nonce
is simply to pick the nonce at random
前提是新鲜值空间足够大
这样就能以很高的概率
assuming the nonce space is sufficiently
large so that with high probability the
使得新鲜值在密钥使用期间内不会重复
现在在这种情况下
nonce will never repeat for the life of
the key. Now in this case, nonce
基于新鲜值的加密就变成了随机加密
based encryption simply reduces to
randomized encryption. However, the
不过这里的好处是，发送方在发送不同信息时
不需要维护状态
benefit here is that the sender does not
need to maintain any state from message to
所以这很有用，比如，如果加密正好发生在
message. So this is very useful, for
example if encryption happens to take
多台设备上，例如，我可以有一台笔记本
place on multiple devices. For example, I
might have both a laptop and a smart
和一个智能手机。它们可能使用同样的密钥
但这种情况下，如果我需要维护状态
phone. They might both use the same key.
But in this case if I require state for
为了加密的话，那么我的笔记本和智能手机
就必须协调好
encryption, then my laptop and the
smartphone would have to coordinate to
以确保它们不会重复使用相同的新鲜值
如果双方都随机选取新鲜值
make sure that they never reuse the same
nonces. Whereas if both of them simply take
他们不必协调的，因为
nonces at random, they don't need to
coordinate because it was very high
他们不会选中同一个新鲜值的概率非常高
probability they'll simply never choose
the same nonce. Again assuming the nonce
前提依然是新鲜值空间足够大
那么有些情况下无状态的加密是很重要的
space is big enough. So there are some
cases where stateless encryption is quite
特别是当同样的密钥被不同的机器用来加密时
important, in particular where the same
key is used by multiple machines. So I
我想更精确地找到对于基于新鲜值的加密
wanted to find, more precisely, what
security means for nonce based
安全意味着什么。特别地，我想强调，
系统必须保持安全
encryption. And in particular, I want to
emphasize that the system must remain
当新鲜值是由攻击者选择的时候
这一点很重要的原因
secure when the nonce are chosen by
the adversary. The reason it's important
是攻击者可以选择它想攻击的密文
to allow the adversary to choose the
nonces is because the adversary can
设想一下，新鲜值正好是一计数器
choose which cipher text it wants to
attack. So imagine the nonce happens to
计数器的值正好是15
be a counter and it so happens that when
the couter hits the value fifteen, maybe
也许在这一点，攻击者容易破解语义安全
at that point it's easy for the adversary
to break semantic security. So the
那么攻击者会等到第15个包发出时
才会试图破坏语义安全
adversary will wait until the fifteenth
packet is sent and only then he will ask
所以当我们讨论基于新鲜值的加密时
to break semantic security. So when we
talk about nonce based encryption, we
我们一般允许攻击者选择新鲜值
而且系统应当保持安全
generally allow the adversary to choose
the nonce and the system should remain
即使是在这些条件下。那么我们定义
在这种情况下的CPA游戏
secure even under those settings. So let's
define the CPA game in this case and it's
实际上它和之前的游戏很像
攻击者提交一对明文信息MI
actually very similar to the game before.
Basically the attacker gets to submit
MI由MI0和MI1组成。明显它们的长度是一样的
pairs of messages MI, MI0, and MI1.
Obviously they both have to be of the same
攻击者提供新鲜值。作为回应
length. And he gets to supply the nonce.
And in response, the adversary is given
攻击者得到MI0或MI1的加密结果
不过是使用攻击者选择的新鲜值
the encryption of either MI0, or MI1. But
using the nonce that the adversary
当然，和往常一样，攻击者的目标是
chose. And of course, as usual, the
adversary's goal is to tell whether he was
区分他得到的是左边明文的加密
还是右边明文的加密
given the encryption of the left plain
text or the right plain text. And as
之前，攻击者反复进行询问，
他想问多少次都可以
before the adversary gets to iterate these
queries and he can issue as, as many
我们通常记攻击者询问的次数为Q
queries as he wants, we usually let q
denote the number of queries that the
当然，现在唯一的重要限制是
adversary issues. Now the only restriction
of course, which is crucial, is that
尽管攻击者可以选择新鲜值
他每次只能选择不同的新鲜值
although the adversary gets to choose the
nonces, he's restricted to choosing
我们这样要求攻击者的原因是
distinct nonces. The reason we force him
to choose distinct nonces is because
这是实际中的要求。即使攻击者欺骗Alice
that's the requirement in practice. Even
if the adversary fools Alice into
为他加密多个信息，Alice也不会使用同样的新鲜值的
encrypting multiple messages for him,
Alice will never use the same nonce
因此，攻击者不会看到用同样新鲜值加密的明文
again. As a result, the adversary will
never see messages encrypted using the
所以在这个游戏中，我们要求所有新鲜值不同
same nonce and therefore, even in the
game, we require that all nonce be
然后，通常我们说系统是基于新鲜值加密的
distinct. And then as usual we say that
the system is a nonce based encryption
是对选择明文攻击语义安全的
system that's, semantically secure under a
chosen plain text attack if the adversary
如果攻击者无法区分实验0
即获得左边明文加密
cannot distinguish experiment zero where
he's given encryptions of the left
和实验1，即获得右边明文加密
messages from experiment one where he's
given encryptions of the right messages.
我们看一个例子，是基于新鲜值的加密系统
So let's look at an example of a nonce
based encryption system. As before, we
之前，我们有一个安全的PRF，取新鲜值空间R里的元素
为输入，输出明文空间M里的字符串
have a secure PRF that takes inputs in the
nonce space R and outputs strings in the
现在，当选择一个新密钥时，我们重置计数器R为0
message space M. Now when a new key is
chosen, we're going to reset our counter R
现在我们加密特定的明文M
to be zero. And now we encrypt the
particular message M, what we will do is
我们将计数器R加一，然后使用伪随机函数加密M
we will increment our counter R, and then
encrypt the message M using the
并应用这个R值。之前，密文包含两个部分
pseudorandom function applied to this
value R. And as before, the cipher text is
我们当前计数器的值
going to contain two components, our
current value of the counter and then the
然后明文M的一次性密码本加密结果
我的问题是
one time pad encryption of the message M.
And so my question to you is whether this
这是一个安全的基于新鲜值的加密系统吗？
跟之前一样，答案是肯定的
is a secure, nonce based encryption system.
So the answer as before is yes, but only
但是仅当新鲜值空间足够大
这样我们增加计数器R
if the nonce space is large enough. So as
we increment the counter R, it will never
R也不会回卷到0，这样新鲜值总是唯一的
cycle back to zero so that the nonce
will always, always be unique. We argue
用之前一样的方法，我们能证明其安全性
因为PRF是安全的，我们知道
security the same way as before. Because
the PRF is secure, we know that this
这个加密系统和使用真随机函数不可区分
encryption system is indistinguishable
from using a truly random function. In
换句话说，如果我们对计数器
应用一个真随机函数
other words, if we apply a truly random
function to the counter and XOR the
然后把结果和明文M异或。但现在
由于新鲜值R从不重复
results with, the plain text M. But now
since the nonce R never repeats, every
每次我们计算F(R)，我们都能得到
一个真随机的均匀分布且相互独立的
time we compute this F of R, we get a
truly random uniform and independent
字符串，这样我们实际上是使用一次性密码本
在加密每一个明文信息
string so that we're actually encrypting
every message using the one time pad. And
于是，在两个实验中，所有的攻击者
as a result, all the adversary gets to see
in both experiments are basically just a
只能获得一对随机字符串。所以实验0和实验1里
pair of random strings. So both the
experiment zero and experiment one the
攻击者看到的是严格相同的分布
adversary get's to see exactly the same
distribution, namely, the responses to all
对所有选择明文攻击的询问的回应
仅仅是均匀分布的一对字符串
this chosen plain text queries are just
pairs of strings that are just uniformly
这点在实验0和实验1中都是一样的
distributed and this is basically the same
in experiment zero and experiment one and,
所以攻击者无法区分这两个实验
therefore, the attacker cannot distinguish
the two experiments. And since he cannot
由于使用真随机函数时，攻击者
不能取得这个语义安全游戏的胜利
win the semantic security game with a
truly random function he, also, cannot win
他也不能取得使用PRF时，这个游戏的胜利
the semantics security game with the
secure PRF, and, therefore, the scheme is
所以这个机制是安全的。现在我们理解了
对称加密系统安全的意义
secure. So now we understand what it means
for a symmetric system to be secure when
当密钥用于加密多个信息，且要求
the keys used to encrypt multiple messages
the requirement is that it be secure under
对选择明文攻击是安全的。我们说了
唯一的在选择明文攻击是安全的方法
a chosen plan of attack. And we said that
basically, the only way to be secure under
是使用随机加密
a chosen plain text attack is either to
use randomized encryption, or to use, use
或使用基于新鲜值的加密，这里
新鲜值不会重复才行
nonce spaced encryption where the
nonce never repeats. And then in the
下面两节，我们构建两个经典的加密系统
next two segments, we're gonna build two
classic encryption systems that are secure
它们在密钥多次使用时是安全的
when the key is used multiple times.